So today, we are going to
talk about inference scaling.
We briefly hinted on this
in the first lecture,
so there are three stages
for LLM kind of development.
The first one is pre-training.
This stage is historically
takes a lot more time.
It could take several months.
A whole lot of GPUs that
are used for training these.
And then there's the
fine tuning step.
Usually, this is a less,
or historically has been
a less compute-intense process.
If you are talking
about trillions
of data, tokens in
the pre-training side,
on the fine tuning side, this
is orders of magnitude less data
that we use for fine tuning.
And then there is
the inference part,
where we get to use the model.
And we are going to
see different ways
that at inference
time, we can make
the model be better and become
more useful without changing
the parameters of the model
and without any fine tuning
of the models.
So let's first start with the
Large Language Monkeys paper.
Again, you are familiar with the
infinite monkey theorem by now
because we discussed
it on Monday.
But to recap, the idea of this
paper is that we have an LLM
and we have a problem as input.
Instead of generating the
response for this problem
only once, we are going to
repeatedly ask the same input
problem again and again.
This could be a
number of times, it
could be 10 times,
100 times, and so on,
and we will see how that
affects the performance.
And then we are going to have
a verifier that can tell us
which one of these responses
were the correct response,
and then that is going to be
the output of this system.
The reason we like that is that
by doing this repeated sampling,
we can make models
that are inferior.
For example, a Llama 3-8b or 70b
that is not as capable as GPT-4o
with single attempt.
But by doing this
repeated sampling
and selecting the correct one
among the generated candidates,
we can significantly
improve the performance
of these inferior models
and make them better
than these larger
and proprietary ones.
And these are-- here
you can see examples
across a really hard math coding
and different styles of math
problem question
answering problems.
Is this clear to everyone?
It just seems like the models
and smaller models already
know the answers to
these hard problems,
and just by doing this
repeated sampling,
we are eliciting and
surfacing those answers.
It's just they just don't tell
us that in the first trial.
Now, this paradigm
of repeated sampling,
works well across
pretty much any domain
that we have tried in so far,
including agentic benchmarks
such as SWE-bench, which mimics
how a software engineer goes
about editing code and
creating new patches.
So here, we are
seeing the coverage,
meaning the fraction
of problems that
are solved by, at least,
one of the samples.
And here on the x-axis, we have
the number of samples going from
1 to 1,000.
And what we are seeing here is
that a models such as DeepSeek
can--
I believe this was the
DeepSeek-V3 model can outperform
models such as Claude 3.5 or
o1 preview after 1,000 samples.
It can solve more coding
and software engineering
problems than those.
And the reason
this is interesting
is that, we are doing--
in this case for
coding problems,
if we have unit
tests that we can
use to select which one of
these samples is correct, then
we have an end-to-end
automated way
to create a more capable
model, in this case,
out of DeepSeek and
open-source model.
Now, again, we saw pre-training
scaling laws in the last class,
and that was, we can predictably
reduce the test laws given
these equations in this paper.
And these equations might
change given the setup,
but there is a predictable
path to increase data, amount
of compute use, and the
number of parameters
in the model and use that to
predict, or reduce the test
laws.
So this is for pre-training,
but it turns out,
we can define a similar
scaling laws, but this time
for inference, or
test time compute,
and that is something that
we showed in this paper.
Basically, we're showing
that the relationship
between coverage and
the number of samples
that are being drawn in
parallel from the model
follow an exponential power law.
So assume this says,
coverage, meaning
how many problems are solved by,
at least, one of the samples,
and then k is the
number of samples.
And a and b are these
kind of coefficients
that we can find through
the curve-fitting parameters
that we can find through this
scaling behavior of the model.
So concretely, as we scaled the
number of samples across a range
of models from
Llama 3 8B, 7, 8B,
and models like Gemma or Pythia.
And this is for various
range of parameter sizes,
going from 70 million
parameters all the way
to 70 billion parameters.
We can see that we can
predict this power law
and have a predicted curve
that for the most part,
very closely follows the actual
practical coverage that we
are seeing as we increase
the number of samples.
So basically, the
way to think about it
is that we can predict to
achieve a certain coverage,
how many samples we
are going to need
and how much resources we
should allocate to achieve that.
And again, these curves
show that this behavior
is true for a range of models
and a range of parameter sizes.
Again, one of the very
interesting properties
that we saw here is that
for a very small model,
like a 70 million parameter, we
also see this scaling behavior.
And, of course, this is true
for much larger models as well,
and it is true across domains.
Now, we looked a bit more
into why we see this power law
behavior in repeated
sampling because it
might be at first a
little non-intuitive,
because if the probability of
the pass at one being correct,
the probability of a correct
response to a question
is, for example, p,
then we can calculate
the probability
of, at least, one
of the answers being correct at
k for an individual problems.
So for a problem i, if we have
the pass at one for problem i,
we can calculate directly what
is pass at k for problem i
with this exponential equation.
I hope this is
clear for everybody,
but basically, this 1 minus p is
the probability of the first k
answers not being
correct, and then
1 minus that is the probability
of, at least, one of these k
answers being correct, so this
is for an individual problem.
But what we are seeing that
across a suite of problems,
we are seeing the power
law, scaling law, meaning
across these problems,
we are seeing
the equations are changing.
So the question that
we wanted to answer
is what behavior should we see
across the problem examples
in a data set that justifies
our power law scaling laws?
And by looking into that
further, what was observed
is that in order to have the
scaling laws that we observed,
the sufficient and
necessary condition for it
is that we have a long
tail of hard problems.
Basically, from a
mathematical perspective,
we are going to need that
because this is the power law
scaling, this is the per problem
exponential scaling laws,
and this is like this sort.
We need to have this curve for
the past at one of problems
in order to justify
this power law scaling.
And empirically, when we
looked into the problems,
we saw that this
condition holds.
And again, what
this condition is
is that we have a long tail of
really hard problems on the most
complex side of things.
For example, let's take a look
at this model and the count
of problems that are
solved at pass at one
and add more and more samples.
It seems like across
all these problems,
a large portion of
problems are simpler
and they're solved
in pass at one.
And as we increase
the complexity
of the problems, where the
pass at one probability
is going to become
lower and lower,
we have a long tail of problems
that have that property.
So these curves
that you see here
from high at simpler problems
and low at harder and harder
problems, meaning lower
and lower paths at one
is the type of problems,
is the type of behavior
that we are seeing
across these tasks,
and that is why we
can see the scaling
laws that we have observed.
Now, what this means for the
science and the engineering
around LLMs is that while
previously companies
would spend hundreds
of millions of dollars,
or billions of dollars
on pre-training alone,
and then a lot
less on fine tuning
and then almost like
nothing at each inference
call because it used
to be like a one time
back and forth between the user
and the query and the model.
Now we have a new
paradigm, where
we can spend a whole lot
more compute on inference,
and use that to increase
the capability of model.
And this compute the inference
compute can be done offline.
We can release our agents
to go solve a problem
and just keep generating
tokens and keep
improving the quality of the
answers that they generate.
Now, when we talk about
this repeated sampling,
something that's
important to have in mind
is the need for
automated verification
because if you have
a bunch of samples,
we still need to know which one
of them are the correct ones
and how to go about
selecting that.
In certain domains, verification
is easier than the others.
For example, for certain
types of math problems,
you can use formal proofs.
So given a proof,
the strategy, we
can run them by these
formal proof software tools
to verify whether each
step is correct or not.
We can write unit
tests for coding.
And in some cases, writing a
unit test arguably, arguably,
is a much simpler task than
writing the entire program that
solves a problem,
so the unit test
can be written, for
example, by humans,
and we can use that
as our verifier.
There are other cases
like AI as a compiler,
and this is one of the projects
in the lab and the direction
that I'm very excited
about, and that
is when we can generate
compiler lower level
code, like CUDA for a source
code like PyTorch with LLM.
And the reason
this is verifiable
is that, for example
here, we can always
compare the output of CUDA
with the source PyTorch
and see if they're the
same for any given input.
So we don't need if we want
to say whether the model has
generated the correct CUDA code
for our source PyTorch code,
we can just see whether their
outputs match for any inputs.
For those of you who
are not familiar CUDA,
I hope you all are, but
it's a lower level language
for writing more hardware
aware and optimized
for hardware code on GPUs.
For example, here,
we have a data set,
or benchmark on CUDA
generation called KernelBench.
And here, again, we are seeing
the same linear improving
coverage in this case
for CUDA code generation
as we increase the
number of samples
that we take from the model.
And in this case,
we have this, again,
by default, perfect
verifier that we
can use for measuring the
correctness of our CUDA
generated code.
And there are other
examples of this.
Basically, any
kind of translation
between two languages.
If you want to port from Python,
or C++ to Java, or vice versa,
again, this is true.
You can measure the
equivalency much easier.
Now there are domains that
we don't have verifier for.
And in those domains,
what we observe
is that there is a
large gap between best
of n methods such
as majority vote
voting and model-based
rankers and what is
the true coverage of the model.
Let's take a look
at one example here.
So here, we compared a
few different methods.
We are going to learn
about reward models
or verifiers on Monday
more, but let's take
a look at these examples.
So we have a number of
samples, and then we
are measuring the
success rate here,
like basically what would be
the output of this system?
Majority voting,
or the green one
is we just see which answer
among the generated answers
has appeared the most,
so based on that,
we just select that
answer or that response
as the output of our system.
Does that make sense?
It's just majority voting.
And the blue line
here is coverage.
This is assuming we had a
perfect selector, or verifier
in this case.
And as you can see here,
there is a large difference
between majority voting, which
plateaus after 10 or 50 samples,
and what we could
possibly get if we
had a perfect verifier, so
this is a very, very large gap.
Especially, and this gap
is even more pronounced
if you have harder problems.
So for example, the
capital MATH here, data set
is a harder, more complex
data set than GSM8K
And here, we compared
other methods
like using a reward model
that measures, gives
a reward per answer, and we
take the best of those, or ways
to combine these tools.
We will learn more about
these reward models.
Basically, they're
LLM-based LLMs
that are trained to score
the response quality.
And even with those,
there is a large gap.
And this is what we call the
generation verification gap.
So the generation,
it turns out, we
can generate a lot
of good responses,
but the verification
is basically this gap.
This tells us how
much we can actually
capture those responses
or those correct answers.
The reason methods such as
majority voting doesn't work is
that, as we look into
the quality of answers,
it turns out that for some
problems that are hardest
to solve, sometimes we see that
they're solved maybe even once,
or two times, or three times
across the 1,000 or 10,000
samples that we
take from the model.
So these correct problems are
actually very rarely solved
by the model with the samples
that we are taking from it,
so it makes sense that a
majority voting mechanism cannot
capture those
because they're rare.
But for many of the
problems in this case,
especially for the
GSM8K, which is simpler
because the answers, or
responses are simpler
to generate, majority voting
works for many of the problems,
but even in this case,
for some of the hardest
problems, the frequency of
correct answers actually
pretty low.
So that makes it harder from
a verification perspective
how do you find them?
How do you find that
which ones are correct?
Now, I want you to--
here are some
discussion questions
that I want to put it here
for something like two minutes
or so, and I want you
to think about it.
And hopefully, we'll
have some volunteers
and volunteer some of you
to answer some of them.
So two minutes for this.
Maybe we talk after.
[SIDE CONVERSATION]
OK, let's get back.
Who wants to answer question 1?
I'm very interested
in how you would
build on this, if you were
to do some research here,
or what takeaways you
got from these papers.
Anyone?
Yes.
One takeaway is that sampling
any answers and issues.
If you have a good
verifier, it's greatly
helps with your accuracy.
And the second takeaway is that
the quality of the verifier
is very important
in this approach.
That's right.
Anything else?
Yes.
[INAUDIBLE] it is possible to
write a model to [INAUDIBLE]
that way make examples.
For example, like the model
[INAUDIBLE] descriptions
and the model for the
solution that is a [INAUDIBLE]
even if you're not sure
the solution is right.
Are you talking about
revising a solution--
Yeah.
--by next round?
We're going to hear
about it in a minute.
Sounds good.
Yes.
I'm looking at it
two directions.
One is the [INAUDIBLE]
and accuracy.
And for that, I would look
at a hybrid approach, where
I would develop a
knowledge graph along
with advanced documentation.
And then any returns
to the rank method.
When [INAUDIBLE] comes time the
score is lesser on the accuracy
and more or less
rely on the knowledge
to give me more accurate
answers, that way you
can increase the speed in
the answer while [INAUDIBLE].
So you're suggesting use
RAC to boost or compare?
With the knowledge first,
and then only when they
feel that the accuracy is
not coming up to the mark,
we go through the
right documentation
because that also lowers
the time, and there is--
So you're asking that can help
with efficiency in the time
domain?
Is trying to reduce the
dependency and damage
to increase the
accuracy and precision.
One more.
Maybe you were waiting.
Yeah, so something that I've
thought about also is just--
and even if it's easy to medium
level of difficulty with respect
to verification or
verifiable domains,
it would be cool to see how
pass at k changes with respect
to k, when we employ initial
search techniques, almost
like a self-study approach.
If there's some way
to maybe consolidate,
let's let the model
explore this domain,
gather insights as
if we're not asking
it to sample any solutions yet.
And maybe that can give
way to some output context,
and we could then funnel
into parallel sampling.
We might see maybe better
trends with respect--
Absolutely.
And we're going to learn
about some of them.
There are ways to
improve test time scaling
beyond just repeated sampling,
including self-study, search,
and tool use.
Maybe one more.
Yes.
Well, one interesting
extension might
be to [INAUDIBLE] verifiers.
Without a good verifier,
then the best you can do
is [INAUDIBLE] what you showed
in the previous slide, which
usually doesn't work very
well for hard problems.
But maybe there
are some problems,
where it's hard to verify the
answer is correct because it's
too expensive, or it's
just too hard naturally,
but it's easy to
find an answer wrong,
so you can project
like bad answers.
Maybe that would be more
obvious in terms of testing.
And then you can just
keep [INAUDIBLE] something
[INAUDIBLE].
So one interesting
direction would
be trying to look at
different domains, where
there is much difficulty.
And also maybe verification
is not fully accurate,
or maybe it's a bit
lost, but verify
it's its own model
because it's a simulation.
It's like a physics, or a
molecular dynamics simulation,
or something, and then how
you would deal with that.
Basically, there are
other ways to filter out
the incorrect answers.
Maybe use a simulation,
or some other tool use,
or another model to do that,
depending on the domain.
So all of the data set here,
the 10,000 different samples per
problem is available
on Hugging Face.
If anybody is
interested to go around
how to shrink that
generation verification gap,
that could be potentially a good
research project for the course.
Yes, last question.
Yeah.
Can one try to generate multiple
verifiers like maybe generate
10,000 verifiers and then do
majority voting on the result
of the bad verifiers?
Yes.
That's also a very
interesting research question.
So on Monday, we're going to
learn about this weaver, which
is a work that we've
done on ensembling,
but a week supervised
ensembling of verifiers.
We don't have 1,000 of them, but
we can have 10 or 20 of them,
but that direction is
definitely also interesting.
It's very costly, though,
from a compute perspective.
Maybe we should move on to the--
any other about the other two
questions, anything?
We discussed some of
it in our discussion,
but anything that you
want to share last minute?
Yes.
What is up with the investigated
whether the coverage
number is real, like software
engineering tasks, for example?
Or could you pass
the test cases,
but it's actually
about [INAUDIBLE]?
For example, for
the math problems,
we manually looked into
the answered questions,
and it was something
above like a 90s, 7%,
8% by manually checking that,
but that's also always a case
for failure mode, if your unit
tests don't have true coverage
of the code, so the quality
of the verifier matters.
Yes.
Maybe it's moved up to be
able to generate [INAUDIBLE],
so you're verifying each node?
Yeah, let's talk about
that and what's coming next
and how we can make different
ways of test time scaling.
So with the monkeys
framework, we
saw that repeated
sampling is effective,
but there are other
ways to scale sampling.
And let's take a
look at this paper.
Scaling LLM test time
compute optimally
can be more effective than
scaling model parameters.
We going to touch on
certain aspects of it that
is most relevant to test time
scaling, so there are two ways.
Parallel sampling
is one way for us
to generate multiple
answers per input question.
But there is another way to
generate, or generate answers,
or use test time scaling
to improve the quality,
and that is when we do
sequential revisions.
For example, the model comes
up with one initial steps
of the problem, or
one initial approach
for solving the problem,
and it keeps revising that,
or it keeps improving
and adding to that.
And that is the sequential
approach, so instead
of asking the model
multiple times,
we let the model know that it
can keep revising its answers,
look into that from
a different angles,
and continue doing so
until it's confident
that it's ready to
generate an answer
and then finally output that.
Yes.
So is this by our own
prompting or is it the models?
In this case, let's assume
by our own prompting,
but when you look at
the reasoning models,
they are now trained.
Internally, we see this
kind of behavior in them,
so they do this revisions
sometimes in their own answers.
Now, there is another way
to scale test time compute,
and that is how we
select the answers.
So for the parallel sampling,
we looked into the outcome
like there are n
different responses.
We look into the outcome and
see if they're correct or not.
We mentioned unit
tests and so on,
but there's also this other
way of learning based,
or outcome reward models, where
they look into the outcome
and say whether
they're correct or not.
Of course, their
accuracy, or quality
can be limited, especially
if we go to new domains.
But outcome-based reward
model is another way
that they look into
the final answer
and they generate a score.
Basically, these models are
trained to give a reward based
on an output.
Then there is also the
process reward models.
So the difference between
process and outcome
is that process
reward models are
designed to give a score per
step of the generated solution.
For example, we have
a math problems,
there are five steps
that the model takes
before generating a solution.
Process reward models, again, we
learn about this more on Monday,
I believe, are trained to
give a score for the steps
of the generation.
So that's the difference
between the two.
Now, for best of n
sampling with a verifier,
again, the problem is easy.
We generate parallel
samples, and then we
can use an outcome-based
reward model
to see which one has
the highest score
and then take that
as our answer.
Then there are other ways that
we can bring these reward models
into the processing, into our
test time scaling framework.
For example, here, let's assume
at each level of answering
this question, we have a
budget of four samples.
We take these four
samples, and then here,
use a Process Reward Model
or PRM to in this case, we
select the top two with the
highest score from our PRM.
Then again, we sample
from them and we continue.
And we can have a threshold
for selecting the top two
kind of responses in
this case and expanding
the tree from there.
So here, we are doing
a beam search approach
that uses the process
reward model to guide
how we are sampling our model.
Is that clear?
Yes.
How do you choose the options?
Based on the PRM score.
So the process reward model
is trained to generate
a score imagine
between 0 and 1 based
on the step given the question,
and/or just the step alone.
Is the PRM fine tuned for that?
Yes, PRMs are generally also
fine tuned from language model.
As you can imagine,
they would work better
for in-domain types of tasks, so
if you have a certain benchmark
that you want to optimize
for, of course, training
a PRM on a subset of
that task helps you
with test time
scaling on that task
better than across new task.
But because they're
language model based,
they do exhibit some
generalization across tasks
as well.
Yes.
For the process reward,
is this a reward
that's being
computed in practice?
I don't know what the research
is per token that is being done,
or maybe blocks of tokens
and then it's being computed.
Yes.
It's not per token.
It's per step.
And this is something
we're going to learn about
in future lectures.
Imagine, these are
like a math problem,
and then there are
steps to answer that.
One way to do it is to
have humans annotate
the quality of each step like
yes or no, this is good or bad,
and then training the model
based on each step, which
could be like you can assume
it's like one intellectually
meaningful chunk of the
result, or it could be you
can define it as a
sentence and so on.
And, of course, as
it's very intuitive,
if you combine the two of
outcome based reward model
and parallel based upon
sequential revisions,
you get better results.
This field is
still there's a lot
of unknown questions around
this, but combining the two.
For example, one simple
way to combine that
is instead of one sample
and revisions, you do two
and you get to
two final answers,
and then you use the best one,
either using your PRM or ORM
to select how the two are.
But you're augmenting
each parallel sample
with these sequential
revisions, and you
can use a PRM to
guide that search
for each sequential revision.
Something that's interesting
is that the PRM, there
are many off the shelf PRM's
that you can use for your tasks.
So you can go and say,
take a pre-trained PRM
and use that to guide the
search for your own task.
And you can potentially
find a PRM that
is most relevant to the type
of task that you're doing,
and you want to do
test time scaling on,
or you can train
your own PRM and ORM
based on your own data as well.
So this paper looked into the
math data set and something like
12k train set 500 test
questions, used the palm model.
And what was interesting
here is that they defined
a notion of difficulty
for measuring
these different
scaling behaviors,
and for that, they
looked into the pass
at one performance of the
model on each problem.
And by just measuring
that, they define OK, these
are the problems
that are hard, these
are the problems based on
how many of the generated
answers are correct across a
body of a number of samples.
They had five different bins for
the complexity of the problem,
and they did that, as we see to
get some conclusion about what
test time scaling works better
for harder or easier task.
They also train their
own process reward model,
and even they fine tune a model
for creating these revisions.
But right now, every model that
we use pretty much it's capable.
It's just as long as
it's instruction-tuned,
is capable of doing revisions,
if you ask the model to do so.
And there are some
interesting observations here.
For example, here is
the majority voting
for these problems.
The accuracy as the
generation budget
increases, and then the
purple one is the ORM one.
And the green one is the PRM
one, and then the blue one,
if you really try to optimize
different ways of mixing
and matching things.
And this area is the one that
still is an open research
like how do we do that?
How do we go about mixing
and matching revisions
and parallel scaling to
optimize the test time
scaling because at
the end of the day,
we want for each accuracy, we
want the minimum generation
budget to hit that accuracy?
And in a few slides ahead,
we talk about one method
to optimize this scaling and
budget performance per budget.
They also looked into these
different bins of difficulty,
so number 5 is the most
difficult questions
because the accuracy is
the lowest and number 1.
And then here on
the right, there's
these colors is the
sequential to parallel ratio.
And while they're saying that
OK for the easier problems,
it seems like this darkest the
darkest purple color achieves
highest accuracy,
and that's where
we have a lot more sequential
tokens compared to parallel.
When the problems are more
difficult, and to some extent,
those are some of the
more interesting problems,
this optimality
is harder to say.
It's harder to say whether it's
sequential or the ratio changes
even from bucket four
to bucket five on how
you should allocate that.
Another observation from
this paper was that--
and this is still
a work in progress,
and I believe still the
true observation as of today
is that for easy and
medium questions,
it seems like
additional test time
compute can be more
favorable than scaling
pre-training of the model.
So here, we have these two.
The easy are the
green, medium is blue,
and orange is the
hard questions.
It seems if we look into the
ratio of inference tokens
to pre-training tokens, it is
positive for the easy and medium
problem, but for
the hardest problem,
it seems larger models
like a more pre-training,
or larger models
still do better if you
are from a tokens
optimized perspective.
And this is something
that we have
seen in many of our research
in the lab or around the lab
as well.
It seems like models, simpler
open source models, or smaller
models are becoming
more and more useful
as we take more test time
compute, apply more test
time compute on them.
But still, for the very,
very hard problems,
still the frontier
models, which presumably
use more pre-training
and they are larger,
they do better even if we had a
whole lot like infinite budget
for test time scaling.
Of course, we don't
have infinite budget,
but any reasonably
large test time scale.
Yes.
In this case, how do you
inference for this pre-training?
Because it seems
like for inference,
you use it much
like [INAUDIBLE],
whereas for pre-training
tokens, it's you use it once
and you can use it twice.
Yes, that is true.
But in general, from
a-- but this is still--
so basically, yes,
pre-training is done once,
but scaling is every
time we run the model.
But still, this is an
interesting observation
from the perspective of, are
we done doing pre-training
because we can just keep
sampling from the models we
have, or no, pre-training
is still helpful
and we should do more and more?
Not everyone can
pre-train a large model.
So even if
pre-training was better
than test time
scaling in any scale,
not everyone can do that because
it's a very expensive process.
So this is very interesting
that for many problems,
we can do test
time scaling, even
if we do it every time for a
new problem, because that's
feasible.
But also, on the other hand,
for the hardest problems,
we still need to
do pre-training,
and better models
still do better.
That makes sense.
I was just curious
precisely in the graph
when it says like the ratio is 1
for retraining of, for instance,
retraining.
Does that mean that it's
[INAUDIBLE] training,
there was also one training
used for a single task?
No.
No, it's not exactly that.
It's more like some
ratio of pre-training
to inference compute.
It's not a one-to-one because it
doesn't make sense in that case.
My question is, why is it
that those larger models still
count better?
Can we take a smaller model
and yet make it an expert
on hot questions?
You can always fine tune
a model to become better
on a certain set of
questions, but we
are talking about a more general
perspective of let's have
a whole lot of data
that's general, not
specific to a specific task and
just compare the common recipes
that we use for training models.
Let's just follow that
and then see how much
they do better at test time.
Any other questions?
So maybe we discussed some
of these already, but here
are some more questions
that I give you another two
minutes, let me check the time.
Yes, we do have time,
to think about this.
This helps you absorb
some of the topics
that we learned, or heard
about in the previous slides,
and then we discuss
them in two minutes.
OK, should we start?
Anyone wants to add
any comments here,
or any questions you might have?
Yes.
So do you try sequential and try
too-- what about tree search?
And in that case,
you're doing the--
You're mixing the both.
Yeah, you're kind
of mixing, right?
Yeah.
There is no universal
answer that can be there.
But the general sentiment
was that does better,
like some sort of combining
the two than doing--
[INAUDIBLE] you do, so reduce
a lot of the compute that
you're doing or reuse
[INAUDIBLE] that you're doing
because it's a tree--
Yes, yes.
That is when we discussed the
beam search stuff and the PRM,
like bringing a PRM to
cut the tree at each level
and explore only the
more promising branches.
Anything else?
Yes.
[INAUDIBLE] as the thinking
that that's the easier problem,
the more perhaps you
have towards the success
of solving it.
Therefore, it could be
more sequential [INAUDIBLE]
problem because you would--
there are few students solving,
so you would need
many parallel process
to find at least
one viable solution.
And we started thinking
a little bit also
like to do this in a chain
of thoughts kind of way,
where you are doing
a chain of thought,
but verifying through all the
steps into our chain of thoughts
instead, and then pruning
from these branches
that are violating anything.
Yeah.
So in terms of sequential,
you're saying that for easier
ones, easier problems--
for harder problems,
you mean you need more
exploration potentially
for easier--
To the correct answer.
Or for easier problems,
because like any kind of path
might lead us to
the correct answer,
we might not need to explore
different parallel solutions.
Yeah, that is an intuitive kind
of way of thinking about this.
Any other thoughts?
In general, this is a
very interesting kind
of problem to think about.
How do you-- let's assume that
these tokens that you generate
is like a knob that you
have to increase problem,
the quality of the responses,
how do you allocate this knob?
And how do you elicit these
generations from the model?
So let's think about
in the following,
I'm going to talk about
one way to optimize
these kind of test time scaling
to generate optimized answers.
And that is the Archon paper,
an architecture search framework
for inference time scaling.
So the problem
state-- and your TA
is one of the
co-authors of this work.
So the problem in this
paper is that, again, we
are interested to see
how we can mix and match
different inference time
scaling methods to build
the optimize the frontier
of capability or correctness
versus cost.
And the other thing that--
again, all of these questions
basically saying the same thing
that how we can optimize
assigning inference
compute two different tasks.
And basically, design mechanisms
that gets us to the high quality
answers while not wasting too
many tokens and generations.
So here is the arc--
like in this case,
we thought of inference
scaling in this project
as an inference
architecture design problem.
So here is how the
Archon framework works.
On the input side, we had
a set of target benchmarks
that we wanted to get good
results on these benchmarks.
So these are the benchmarks
we are optimizing for.
There is an inference
called budget.
And then there's also a
set of available LLMs,
because we can always mix and
match different models also
to get to a correct answer
for a input question.
And then we have a set of
inference time techniques, which
I'm going to describe
in the following slides.
And then we designed
this optimizer.
It's called itest.
It's inference time architecture
search that basically tells us
how to put together
these different models
and different inference
time techniques together,
whether it's parallel sampling,
sequential, and all that,
in order to get
high-quality results given
the budget, the inference
called budget that we have-- how
to optimize the quality
of results based on that.
And then the output
is this architecture
that mixes and matches
these different techniques
and models together.
So let's take a look at
different inference time
operations.
So first, we have the general--
we call it the generation,
but this is basically just
sampling from the model.
And this can be part of the
repeated sampling approach.
So if we generate n--
we use n generations
at a time, that
means we have generated n
different responses to our input
question.
So that's one type of
inference time scaling.
Another one is fusion, which was
surprisingly a very effective
method.
So fusion is, let's say, we
have K different responses,
and we want to generate
one output response out
of these K. Fusion
takes an LLM and asks
an LLM the same exact
question that I just said.
Basically, it says,
here's the input question.
Here are K different responses
to this input question.
Given all of this, generate or
synthesize one output response
for the input question.
Basically, we are showing all of
the K generations to the model,
such that the LLM can generate
an output answer while being
aware of all the possible ways
that this question is answered.
And this is-- it goes under the
category of sequential update.
We have this parallel
samples, but then we
are kind of fusing
them into one answer.
Then there is the
critic, which basically,
for any given response,
we can ask a model
to generate or
describe the weaknesses
or strengths of these response.
And that could be one kind
of inference scaling action.
And then we have the ranker.
This is-- again, these
are all prompting based
optimization for the model.
We haven't trained the model
to do this specific test time
scaling task.
We just ask the model in
the instruction prompt that,
can you rank these
generated responses
from the previous step
based on their quality?
And then the verifiers
generates the-- returns
the response while also talk
about the reasoning of why
it came to this kind of way
to score a certain answer.
I'll get to the
next two unit tests
generation and
evaluation in a bit.
But just to show you how
effective these different
inference time scaling
techniques are,
let's take a look at this
win rate for what tasks--
we don't have the task here.
But it's one of the task
of one of these benchmarks
that I don't know if
you remember the task.
Yeah.
Some question answering
reasoning benchmark.
So here, let's take a look
at how these things work.
So first, we have--
let's say, we have a number of
repeated samples from the model.
It goes from 1 to
10 on the left side.
Let's focus on the
graph on the left side.
And then the orange one is
the kind of worst possible way
of approaching it.
We just randomly
select one and look
at the quality and the
correctness of this response.
The green one is when we
use the model to rank them,
to rank the responses, and
we select the top one ranked
by the model and report that.
That already does better
than the orange one.
The blue one is
Oracle selection,
meaning let's assume
we are not mixing
these responses in any way.
We just select the
best one generated.
Let's say, we have
an Oracle verifier
that can tell us which
one of these is correct.
And that obviously
does better than just
asking the model to rank them
because it's an Oracle verifier.
And then we get to
the red one, which is
where when we use the fusion.
So basically, for each point
here, let's say, we are at 5,
the red data point is basically
we have given these five
responses to the model and
ask the model to synthesize
one answer, one final answer,
given all this information.
And it's so interesting, and
this paradigm is so powerful
that that can on its own
improve the quality of responses
over Oracle selection.
And then finally, the
purple one is where we--
instead of fusing
all the responses,
we first selected the
top five, and then we
went about fusing them.
So it seems like some sort
of a filtering of the two
does better.
Now on the right side, we are
doing a different experiment,
and that is we are--
on the left side.
We had only one model
generating everything.
On the left side,
we had-- we were
using-- we were adding models.
So first one is just one
model generating one answer,
two the baseline is two
different models generating
one answer, and 10 is
10 different models,
each generating one answer.
And we see that, of
course, the random result
becomes worse because the
model we looked on the left
was I think it was among the
better models in this ensemble.
But we still see the same
trend, even if these responses
are coming from different
models, basically the same trend
of how these all
follow each other.
Yes.
Which model is fusing?
If you're using 10
different models,
you're asking somebody
else to rank or fuse your--
I think it's the
model number one
in this case, the
same [INAUDIBLE] that
was in all of those.
And this was the way we
created the ensemble was first
with the best model and then
added the second best model
and so on.
Now let's take a
look at a couple
other inference time techniques.
And that is unit test
generation and evaluation.
I think one of you was
mentioning something like this
earlier as well, that
where we can ask the model
to generate these
unit tests, say
when it gets to coding task
or math, math problem-solving
or other reasoning tasks.
And the unit test
evaluation is even crazier.
Like instead of
running the unit test,
you're asking the model to
evaluate a generated answer
against a unit test.
For example, here
is a prompt check
for-- so the coding
problem in this case
is check for balanceness of
round brackets in an input
string.
That's a coding question.
And then here is
an example input.
Here is the type of unit test
that the model could generate.
For example, given a string
with an odd number of brackets,
the solution should output
no, which is like a good unit
test in this case.
Another one is when a closing
bracket is encountered,
it must match the most
recently open brackets
that hasn't been matched yet.
That's another kind of
reasonable unit test.
And then you can ask the
model to actually generate
the code to test this as well.
Now let's take a
look at the types.
I don't know if you guys
see this well but the type.
But this is so
big, there's no way
for me to put it
here with large font.
But this is the type of
architectures that Archon found.
So basically now think
about it this way.
We have different ways
of mixing and matching
models and inference
time techniques,
and we can define these
layers of optimization.
For example, the first layer
in this case is generation.
And then these generations
are from different models
in this case.
And then we have a
critic and a ranker.
So basically, the critic will
criticize these generations
and then we rank them and
then be the optimizer found
that we could have a bunch
of users at this point,
like each fuses these
responses into one output.
And then we can go from there,
continue this critique ranker.
And this was like a rather
complicated architecture.
And the way that we
optimize this architecture
is that we did some
kind of pre-processing
to reduce the space
of optimization.
For example, the
fact that we found
this sequence of generation
critic ranker and user
do really well.
We did that offline, so we
limited the search space
just because doing this
search is very expensive.
We need to run a lot
of inference calls.
But then the way we optimize it
that we had a held out data set
that-- we had a training data
set that we could optimize
against that and create
this accuracy versus
the number of calls that we are
making to these models, kind
of as a metric that we
are optimizing against.
We want to maximize accuracy.
And for any given budget,
inference budget that we have.
And this is for some
of the coding problems.
This was an optimized
architecture.
Basically, we generate
a ton of samples.
We generate unit tests
and then we evaluate them.
Now, an interesting
property here
is that we found that
stacking more and more layers
of these inference
time techniques,
or making it deep
in a way, actually
does help with our accuracy.
In this case, for example,
the right most pink graph
is where we have an
ensemble, meaning we have
different models in our loop.
And we have three layers
of critiques and fusers
and a final fuser layer.
And this is significantly
better across many
of these tasks over
both just using
a simple the best
model only once,
or the best model eight times
with one layer of fusion.
So it seems like these
additional layers
that we are adding
here is actually--
just like in deep
learning, we are
adding layers in pre-training
and the model gets better.
Seems like these careful
kind of additions
of these inference layers
are helping the model
become more and more accurate.
Across many of the
tasks this is true.
And so now the
optimizer itself, we
used an Bayesian optimizer again
to simplify the search space.
We did a few things.
For example, we
limited the optimizer
to only use one inference
time technique per layer,
and the first layer was
always just the generator.
And then we had this cascade
of ranker, critic, verifier.
They could go
anywhere, but we made
certain kind of modifications
to the search space.
For example, a critic should
go before a ranker or a fuser
always because we did some
testing locally and saw
this is a better choice.
And then a unit
test generator must
be followed by an evaluator up.
And again, we use a Bayesian
optimizer to do this.
This is often a very
powerful methodology,
a ton of good open
source software
to do Bayesian
optimization for you.
Basically, you have
this search space
that you want to configure it
with different kind of choices
for the architecture.
And the output side,
you have the accuracy
and you want to
optimize for that.
And this does better than greedy
search or random selection.
We are much more sample
efficient in terms
of number of configurations
that Archon searches
until it reaches a final
kind of architecture,
and we can define different
objectives for it.
For example, available
models, inference time,
inference, core budget is
one of them or some of them.
The thing that I want you to
pay attention to in this graph
is that this interesting
property that Archon
is, at the end, generating
one response at the very end.
So it's like you're optimizing
paths at one at the very end.
And what was interesting
here is that while using just
the open source models,
we could match or exceed
these closed source
models at the time,
the frontier closed
source model at the time,
by a large margin across
many of these tasks in terms
of paths at one.
Here's the average path
at one improvement.
And not only that,
we could train
Archon to be task specific.
So when we are doing the
Bayesian optimization,
we only look into a certain
task and we test on that,
or we could train Archon
to be general purpose.
So we wanted it to do
better good across many--
to do well across many tasks.
And even that the general
purpose one does really,
really well and better
than the frontier
models across these tasks.
And that was a very
interesting observation
that you can design these
inference time architectures
that do well beyond the
task or the limited tasks
that they're trained on.
So on average, in this case,
we were outperforming GPT-4.0
or Claude 3.5 Sonnet in passage
one by an average of 14.1%
across these instruction
following reasoning and math
encoding problems.
Here are some questions, that
I want you to think about.
But since we're out of time.
Hopefully, you think
about it yourself.
And hope you have
a happy weekend.